I'm five years old, and I am very proud.
عمري خمس سنوات و أنا فخورة جداً.
My father has just built the best outhouse
أتم أبي بناء أفضل منزل ريفي
in our little village in Ukraine.
في قريتنا الصغيرة في أوكرانيا.
Inside, it's a smelly, gaping hole in the ground,
من الداخل، له رائحة، كالفجوة داخل الأرض،
but outside, it's pearly white formica
لكنه من الخارج كفورمايكا بيضاء لؤلؤية
and it literally gleams in the sun.
وله لمعان تحت الشمس.
This makes me feel so proud, so important,
هذا ما جعلني أشعر بالفخر، بالأهمية،
that I appoint myself the leader of my little group of friends
لدرجة أني جعلت نفسي قائدة على مجموعتنا الصغيرة من أصدقائي
and I devise missions for us.
وقد ابتكرت مهمات مختلفة لنا.
So we prowl from house to house
كنا نتجول من منزل لمنزل
looking for flies captured in spider webs
نبحث عن الحشرات في شبكات العناكب
and we set them free.
ونطلقها حرة.
Four years earlier, when I was one,
أربع سنين سابقة، عندما كنت في الواحدة من عمري،
after the Chernobyl accident,
بعد كارثة تشرنوبل،
the rain came down black,
هطلت الأمطار سوداء،
and my sister's hair fell out in clumps,
تساقط شعر أختي في شكل كتل،
and I spent nine months in the hospital.
وقضيت أنا 9 أشهر في المستشفى.
There were no visitors allowed,
لم يكن مسموحا بالزوار،
so my mother bribed a hospital worker.
لذا قامت أمي برشوة أحد العاملين بالمستشفى،
She acquired a nurse's uniform,
وحصلت على زي الممرضات،
and she snuck in every night to sit by my side.
وكانت تتسلل كل ليلة لتجلس بقربي.
Five years later, an unexpected silver lining.
خمس سنوات تلت، لاح لنا فرج غير متوقع.
Thanks to Chernobyl, we get asylum in the U.S.
شكرا لتشرنوبل، لقد حصلنا على اللجوء في أمريكا.
I am six years old, and I don't cry when we leave home
عمري الآن 6 سنوات، ولا أبكي عندما نغادر المنزل
and we come to America,
وأتينا لأمريكا،
because I expect it to be a place filled with rare
لأني أتوقعها أن تكون مكانا مليئا بالنفائس
and wonderful things like bananas and chocolate
والأشياء الرائعة كالموز والشوكولاته
and Bazooka bubble gum,
و لبانة "البازوكة" الفقاعية،
Bazooka bubble gum with the little cartoon wrappers inside,
لبانة "البازوكة" الفقاعية مع الشخصيات الكرتونية المغلفة بداخلها،
Bazooka that we'd get once a year in Ukraine
"البازوكة" التي قد نحصل عليها مرة واحدة فقط خلال العام في أوكرانيا
and we'd have to chew one piece for an entire week.
وكنا لنمضغ قطعة واحدة لمدة أسبوع كامل.
So the first day we get to New York,
لذا في اليوم الأول لوصولنا إلى نيويورك،
my grandmother and I find a penny
وجدت أنا وجدتي بنسا واحدا
in the floor of the homeless shelter that my family's staying in.
على أرضية ملجأ للمشردين والذي كانت تقيم فيه أسرتي.
Only, we don't know that it's a homeless shelter.
ولكننا لم نكن نحسب أنه ملجأ للمشردين.
We think that it's a hotel, a hotel with lots of rats.
كان اعتقادنا أنه فندق، فندق مليئ بالجرذان.
So we find this penny kind of fossilized in the floor,
وجدنا هذا البنس وكأنه متحجر إلى الأرضية،
and we think that a very wealthy man must have left it there
واعتقدنا أن من تركه لابد أن يكون غنيا جدا،
because regular people don't just lose money.
لأن الناس العاديين لا يفقدون نقودهم هكذا.
And I hold this penny in the palm of my hand,
وحملت هذا البنس على راحة يدي،
and it's sticky and rusty,
وكان متسخا وصدئ،
but it feels like I'm holding a fortune.
ولكنني كنت كما لو كنت أحمل ثروة.
I decide that I'm going to get my very own piece
وقررت أنني سأحصل على قطعتي الخاصة
of Bazooka bubble gum.
من لبانة "البازوكة" الفقاعية.
And in that moment, I feel like a millionaire.
وفي تلك اللحظة، كنت أشعر كما لو أني مليونيرة.
About a year later, I get to feel that way again
بعد حوالي العام، أحسست بذلك الإحساس مجددا
when we find a bag full of stuffed animals in the trash,
عندما وجدنا حقيبة مليئة بدمى الحيوانات في سلة المهملات
and suddenly I have more toys
وفجأة كان عندي المزيد من الألعاب
than I've ever had in my whole life.
أكثر بكثير مما كان عندي في السابق.
And again, I get that feeling when we get a knock
ومرة أخرى، جاءني نفس الإحساس عندما سمعنا طرقا
on the door of our apartment in Brooklyn,
على باب شقتنا في بروكلين،
and my sister and I find a deliveryman
ووجدت وأختي أنه موصل الطلبات
with a box of pizza that we didn't order.
يحمل علبة بيتزا لم نطلبها.
So we take the pizza, our very first pizza,
أخذنا منه البيتزا، وكانت أول بيتزا نتذوقها،
and we devour slice after slice
والتهمناها قطعة بعد الأخرى
as the deliveryman stands there and stares at us from the doorway.
بينما كان موصل الطلبات يقف هناك عند المدخل محدقا بنا.
And he tells us to pay, but we don't speak English.
وطلب منا أن ندفع، ولكننا لا نتحدث الإنجليزية.
My mother comes out, and he asks her for money,
وحضرت أمي إلى الخارج، وطلب منها النقود،
but she doesn't have enough.
ولكنها لم تكن تملك المال الكافي.
She walks 50 blocks to and from work every day
كانت تسير مسافة 50 تجمع من وإلى العمل يوميا
just to avoid spending money on bus fare.
قثط لتتجنب أن تدفع أجرة البص.
Then our neighbor pops her head in,
وبعدها أطلت جارتنا برأسها،
and she turns red with rage when she realizes
وتحول لونها إلى الأحمر من شدة الغضب عندما أدركت
that those immigrants from downstairs
أن هؤلاء المهاجرين من الطابق الأسفل
have somehow gotten their hands on her pizza.
حصلوا بصورة ما على البيتزا التي طلبتها.
Everyone's upset.
الجميع كانوا مستائين.
But the pizza is delicious.
ولكن البيتزا لذيذة.
It doesn't hit me until years later just how little we had.
لم اكن أشعر بقلة ما نملك إلا بعد سنين.
On our 10 year anniversary of being in the U.S.,
في المناسبة العاشرة لوجودنا في أمريكا،
we decided to celebrate by reserving a room
قررنا أن نحتفل بأن نحجز غرفة
at the hotel that we first stayed in when we got to the U.S.
في الفندق الذي أقمنا فيه عندما وصلنا حديثا إلى أمريكا.
The man at the front desk laughs, and he says,
ضحك الرجل الذي في الاستقبال، وقال لنا،
"You can't reserve a room here. This is a homeless shelter."
"لا يمكنكم حجز غرفة هنا، هذا ملجأ للمشردين."
And we were shocked.
وأصابتنا الدهشة.
My husband Brian was also homeless as a kid.
زوجي برايان كان أيضا بدون مأوى في طفولته.
His family lost everything, and at age 11,
فقدت أسرته كل شيء، وفي الحادية عشرة من عمره،
he had to live in motels with his dad,
كان عليه أن يعيش بين الموتيلات مع أبيه،
motels that would round up all of their food
تلك الموتيلات التي تقوم بأخذ كل الطعام الذي يملكونه
and keep it hostage until they were able to pay the bill.
وتحتجزه عندها حتى يتمكنوا من دفع الفاتور.
And one time, when he finally got his box
وفي مرة، حينما حصل على أول علبة
of Frosted Flakes back, it was crawling with roaches.
رقائق محمصة له، كانت تعج بالصراصير.
But he did have one thing.
ولكنه كان يملك ذلك الشيء.
He had this shoebox that he carried with him everywhere
كان يملك صندوق حذاء يحمله معه أينما كان
containing nine comic books,
يحتوي على 9 كتب للقصص المصورة،
two G.I. Joes painted to look like Spider-Man
اثنان ل "جي آي جوز" ملونة كما لو انها للرجل العنكبوت
and five Gobots. And this was his treasure.
وخمسة منها "جوبوت". وهذه كانت ثروته.
This was his own assembly of heroes
كانت هذه مجموعته الخاصة من الأبطال
that kept him from drugs and gangs
والتي وقته من المخدرات والعصابات
and from giving up on his dreams.
ومن أن يتخلى عن أحلامه.
I'm going to tell you about one more
سأخبركم بشيء بعد
formerly homeless member of our family.
والتي تعتبر جزءا أيضا من عائلتنا المشردة.
This is Scarlett.
هذه هي سكارلت.
Once upon a time, Scarlet was used as bait in dog fights.
في يوم ما، كانت سكارلت تستخدم في معارك الكلاب كفريسة.
She was tied up and thrown into the ring
كانت تقيد وتلقى في الحلبة
for other dogs to attack so they'd get more aggressive before the fight.
للكلاب الأخرى كي تهاجمها، وبالتالي تزداد شراستها قبل المعركة.
And now, these days, she eats organic food
وحاليا، في هذه الأيام فإنها تأكل الأغذية الطبيعية
and she sleeps on an orthopedic bed with her name on it,
وتنام على وسادة طبية اسمها مكتوب عليها،
but when we pour water for her in her bowl,
ولكن متى ما سكبنا لها الماء على وعائها،
she still looks up and she wags her tail in gratitude.
فإنها تظل ترفع رأسها وتهز ذيلها تعبيرا عن الامتنان.
Sometimes Brian and I walk through the park with Scarlett,
في بعض الأحيان، نتمشى أنا وبرايان في الحديقة و بصحبتنا سكارلت،
and she rolls through the grass,
وتتدحرج على العشب،
and we just look at her
ونمعن النظر إليها
and then we look at each other
ومن ثم ننظر إلى بعضنا البعض
and we feel gratitude.
ونشعر بالامتنان.
We forget about all of our new middle-class frustrations
ننسى الإحباط المصاحب لنا كوننا من الطبقة الوسطى
and disappointments,
وخيبات الأمل،
and we feel like millionaires.
ونشعر كما لو أننا من أصحاب الملايين.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)